Among the freshly blooming dandelions
And the droplets of water which couldn't quite become snow
I thought I could make out a face stained with tears
So I offered my umbrella without a second thought
Is going left or right correct?
The path ended before I could really decide
But surely the right call is the one which spares that special someone
From any painful experiences
So with a little courage, take that plunge forward
If everything's all crooked, take an oblique path
As long as you're moving forward, you'll find the light
Like those little birds that huddle together and cry out in unison
We'll definitely ring in the start of a new season
And so spring will embrace us once more
We'll splash paint on some new pages
We became fast friends, we enjoyed some good food
We might've even argued a little
But we carry those little moments in our hearts
As reasons which compel us toward a future that can't possibly be mistaken
No matter how many times we find ourselves lost among sunlit trees
Today has been carried here by the winds on a one-way ticket
That blooms into a perfect day
Summer Vacation (Part 2)
（零(れい)）オ〜ッ…
Cherry blossom jelly
Cherry blossom
mousse​!
Yellow rice flour
dumplings
Green tea
rice cake
Contains red bean jam!
Jelly with drops of water
Bubbly!
Azuki bean with
ice cream inside
Strawberry
Syrupy pudding
You drew so many.
（零）いっぱい描いたなぁ
Cat confection
Like it's sleeping on top of grass!
Strawberry
Lemon
Goldfish jelly
(maybe soda flavored!)
Cherry blossom
Japanese
white-eye
confection
Japanese
white-eye
confection
Pink sugar candy stars
Starry sky agar
The big bridge nearby
Sparkling stars!
すごくきれいで おいしそうだ
They're so beautiful and look delicious.
でしょう？　でしょう？
I know, right?
シマシマのゼリー
かわいいでしょう？
The striped jelly is cute, isn't it?
And the jelly balls look like drops of water, right?
あと ゼリーのボールも
水玉みたいでしょう？
（ひなた）おじいちゃんが 来年も
やっていいって言ってくれたんだ
Grandpa said we could do it again next year.
Actually, I'd like to do it for the summer festival and the New Year's holiday as well.
本当は 夏祭りとか
年末年始のお参りのときとかに—
すぐにでも またやりたいんだけど
この—
But...
宿題の山が…
I've got this mountain of homework.
Heaping
All these ideas for sweets are popping up in my head,
今こんなに お菓子のアイデアが
浮かんできてるのに—
but I have a ton of homework and mandatory school days during summer vacation!
夏休みに こんなに
宿題と登校日があるなんて…
確かに 多いな…
This is definitely a lot.
Yeah.
We're in our last year of junior high,
but since a lot of things happened in class,
（ひなた）ウチのクラス
３年生なのに いろいろあったから
ホームルームとかで
だいぶ遅れちゃってるから…
homeroom really fell behind.
だから…
So...
零ちゃんは 何歳のころ
プロ棋士になりたいって思ったの？
Rei, how old were you when you first wanted to be a pro shogi player?
（零）そうだな…
Well...
I think I was in fourth grade.
小４のとき …かな
（零）いや…
No.
違うな
That's not right.
That's not quite right.
違うかも
At some point, I realized this was the only path left for me.
気がついたら
この道しか残っていなかった
…ていうか—
Or rather,
これしか
できることがなかったっていうか
this was the only thing I knew how to do.
あっ そうか
Oh, that's right.
Cherry blossom
mousse​!
Jelly with drops of water
Green tea
rice cake
Contains red bean jam!
You love your grandpa's shop,
so you want to help out there, right?
ひなちゃんは
おじいちゃんのお店が好きで—
手伝いたいんだね？
Yeah.
There are lots of things I want to do right now,
and they're all right in front of me,
こんなに今やりたいことが見えてて
目の前にあるのに—
触っちゃいけないのがモヤモヤする
but I can't touch them, which makes me feel sad.
Or maybe it's just that I want a distraction.
それとも
私 目をそらしたいだけなのかな？
宿題の山とか
テストとか 受験とか…
From the mountain of homework,
upcoming tests, or my entrance exams.
でも 志望校って言われても—
People say to choose a high school,
but I can't even picture myself as a high school student.
高校生になった自分が
まだ うまく想像できない
“そこで
うまくやっていけるのか”とかも…
I don't even know if things will go well for me there.
また知らない人たちの中に
入っていくのは…
Joining another group of people I don't know is...
やっぱ
少し うまく言えないんだけど…
I guess I can't really explain it.
Hina, if you'd like,
ひなちゃん
もし良かったらなんだけど
今度の土曜日さ…
and if you're not busy Saturday...
Flowers, it's flowers!
（野口(のぐち)）桐山(きりやま)君！
Kiriyama!
（野口）いやぁ 晴れましたなぁ
ほっほっほっ！
It's a nice and clear day, is it not?
Hoh
本日は お招きいただき
本当にありがとうございます
Thank you very much for inviting us today.
Deep bow
Hello, Teacher.
先生 こんにちは
Welcome.
（野口）ようこそ
（零）あっ…
Yikes
アアッ…　油断してたら
流れるように お約束の事態が…
When I let my guard down,
the obvious misunderstanding happened!
It's okay.
まあまあ どうぞ ゆっくり
楽しんでいってください
Please enjoy yourselves.
The theme is "gravity and the energy of water."
（野口）
テーマは“水のエネルギーと重力”
This is the culmination of the Sho-sci Club's summer research project,
我が将科(しょうか)部の夏の自由研究の集大成
流しそうめんを！
flume noodles!
オオッ！
すごい！　初めて見た！
Wow! This is the first time I've seen one!
Look, Momo! This is flume noodles!
見て モモ
これが流しそうめんだよ
I love slippery food!
モモ つるつる大好き！
Snort
Actually, part of the bamboo thicket in my yard had to
be cut away to make room for an addition to my house,
いやぁ 拙宅(せったく)の庭の竹林を—
一部 増築の流れで
切ることになりましてな
so I thought I better take advantage and make use of it.
せっかくなので
活用せねばと思いまして
Hahahahaha
Hey!
（林田(はやしだ)）お〜い！
Heap
そうめん ゆで上がったぞ
I boiled the noodles!
Here's the first batch.
（林田）
とりあえず 第１弾のそうめんを…
Oh, Mr. Hayashida, let me introduce you.
あっ 先生　ちょっと紹介を…
こんにちは　おジャマします
Hello.
Bow
Thank you for letting us visit.
川本(かわもと)ひなたです　えっと…
I'm Kawamoto Hinata.
Um, and this is my little sister, Momo.
（ひなた）それと 妹のモモです
（モモ）ンンッ…
Oh, right!
あっ…　ああ こんにちは
Hello!
Gasp
そうか…
I see!
Gasp
Hey, Hina, I wanna eat now!
This is the girl Kiriyama was worried about!
この子が あの桐山が
ずっと気にかけていた…
Okay.
Sh-She really is cute!
ホ… ホントに かわいいじゃないか
ええ？　桐山！
Aww
Kiriyama!
We're going to get things flowing now,
今からね ジャンジャン流すから！
たくさん食べていってね！
so make sure you eat your fill!
Right, Kiriyama?!
なあ 桐山！
Hey, Kiriyama!
おい 桐山！
Jab
She's such a cute girl that even a straight-laced guy like Kiriyama would descend into the atmosphere of love!
こんなかわいい子 そりゃ
いくら堅物野郎の桐山君でも—
Jab
そりゃ 恋の大気圏にも
突入しちゃうだろうよ うんうん
Jab
I understand!
Oh no, it's so bittersweet!
ヤダ もう
甘酸っぱいったら もう…
What will I do with him? Sheesh!
まいっちゃうなぁ おいおい
Grind
Mr. Hayashida, um, that hurts.
先生 あの…　痛いんですけど
Grind
Sorry I'm late!
（あかり）すみませ〜ん
かき揚げ揚げてたら
遅くなっちゃって
Cooking the shrimp and veggie fritters took a long time!
ハァ…　あっつ…
It's so hot.
ハァ…
Disheveled
Soaked in
sweat
ハァ〜ッ…
まあ 先生ですか？
いつも零君がお世話になっています
Oh, are you the teacher?
Thank you for always taking good care of Rei.
And thank you for inviting us here today.
本日は
お招きありがとうございます
Deep bow
なんと かき揚げですとな
皆 喜びます　なんとありがたい
Wow, you made shrimp and veggie fritters?
Everyone will be so pleased.
Thank you so much.
（野口）
これは これは　なんとお美しい
And how beautiful!
さあさあ どうぞ こちらへ
Please, come this way!
The situation has naturally
become more complicated again!
（零）
またナチュラルに話がややこしく…
Wait.
…て！
えっ？　先生？
Um, Mr. Hayashida?
Frozen
顔 赤い粘土みたいに
なってますよ
Your face looks like it's made of red clay!
（あかり）フフッ…　ほら
There!
（部員たち）オ〜ッ！
（ひなた）おいしそう！
It looks delicious!
おや 先生　どうしましたかな？
Oh, Mr. Hayashida. What's wrong?
Your face is the color of oxidized iron.
顔が酸化した鉄のような
色になっていますぞ
Maybe you have heatstroke?
もしや 熱射病では？
All right, here we go!
（咲坂）さあ 流しますよ
（咲坂）
皆さん 用意はいいですか？
Is everybody ready?
Serious
Then we'll start with the kids!
それでは まずは子供さんから！
Dazed
Ease up on the water!
（咲坂）水 弱めて！
（部員）アア…
Lower the bamboo chute too!
（咲坂）
竹の傾斜も もっと緩めて！
The child's eyes can't capture the noodles properly!
子供さんの目が
麺を捕捉できてないよ
Her eyes are swimming!
目 むっちゃ泳いでるよ！
アアッ…　ハァ〜ッ…
ハハハッ…
苦戦してますな お嬢さん
It's a struggle, huh, miss?
Instead of aiming for it, the trick is to wait for it.
狙うのではなく 待ち受けるのです
なるほど！
I see!
Yummy!
（モモ）おいしい！
（ひなた）かき揚げも おいしい！
The fritters are yummy too!
なんか楽しい！　わ〜い！
This is fun!
Yay!
Sense of
accomplishment
Yes!
（野口）は〜い！
そして お次は お待ちかね…
Okay!
It's now time for the long-awaited...
Ba-baaam
starving-man event!
Serious
飢えた男子タイム
Here we go!
どんどん いきますよ！
Grab
Here.
はい
Whoosh
（咲坂）はやっ！
（太田）ちょ！
That's fast!
Whoosh
Whiz
Wait!
Zooom
I can't see it!
（部員）見えない！
Zooom
I got a pink one! A pink one!
（太田）
ピンク当たり！　ピンク当たり！
Yes! Woo-hoo!
Pink
やった！　ウヒョ〜！
I did it! I did it! I did it!
（野口）ピンクは とり天と交換
（太田）とり天！
For pink, you get chicken tempura.
Chicken tempura...
Green! I got a green one!
俺 緑！　緑 取ったぞ！
Bzzt!
（野口）ブブ〜！　緑 ハズレです
（林田）はい？
Green is nothing.
What?
Please go to the end of the line.
最後尾についてください
わあ ピンクだ
A pink one!
I'll go get my chicken tempura!
とり天もらってこなくっちゃ
あの…　ちょっと
Um, excuse me!
Swish
Nothing
Nothing's flowing down here!
全然 流れてこないんですけども
I got another pink!
ピンク もう１本入りました！
おいおいおい　俺にも食べさせろよ
Hey, come on already!
Let me eat too!
この麺
全部 ゆでたの俺なんですけど
I'm the one who boiled all these noodles!
Delicious!
（部員）うめえ！
（太田）とり天 おいしい！
The chicken tempura is great!
（林田）くそ〜…
Damn it!
Hey, let me get at least one.
なあ １杯でいい
１杯分でいいから俺の所まで…
なっ？
Just one is fine.
Let one come to me. Okay?
Mr. Hayashida, have you not gotten even one yet?
（零）
先生 取れてないじゃないですか
零ちゃん 楽しそう
Rei looks like he's having fun!
（部員）よし 来た！
うん すっごく楽しそう
Yeah, he looks like he's having a lot of fun.
いいなぁ
こんな楽しそうな高校もあるんだな
This is nice.
I didn't know there were fun high schools like this.
Yes! Chicken tempura!
（部員）よし とり天 とり天！
（笑い声）
Yeah.
そうね
（あかり）そうだ ひな
（ひなた）私…
I've got it, Hina.
Maybe I should try to get into this school.
Why don't you try to get into this school?
（あかり）この高校受けてみれば？
（ひなた）ここ受けてみようかな…
Summer Vacation (Part 2)
New Year
（ひなた）年が明けて １月
Early January of the following year.
Question 30
Using the below figure,
find the angle of x
provided that BA-BC,
and ℓ and m are parallel.
Question 30
Using the below figure,
find the angle of x
provided that BA-BC,
and ℓ and m are parallel.
（ひなた）もうすぐ受験です
Entrance exams are coming up.
Stretch
Hmmmm
S
h
o
g
i
C
h
e
c
k
m
a
t
e
P
r
o
b
l
e
m
s
（ひなた）ね… ねえ　あの…
H-Hey...
Um...
零ちゃん
Rei.
About this figure...
この図形のとこなんだけど…
Slide
これは…
Is this...
え〜っと どれどれ…
Let's see here.
ああ これはね
補助線を引くといいんだよ
Oh, for this, you should draw an additional line.
Wh-Where should I draw it?
ど… どの辺りに引くといいの？
まず いちばん寂しそうな所に
引いてごらん
First try drawing it in the loneliest-looking spot.
Cozy
（ひなた）そう 私は—
That's right.
Cozy
I decided my first choice would be Komahashi Private High School, where Rei goes.
零ちゃんのいる私立駒橋(こまはし)高校を
第１志望に決め—
Cozy
こうやって
勉強を教えてもらっているのです
He's been helping me study like this.
“橋高に行きたい”
そう初めて零ちゃんに言ったとき…
"I want to go to Hashi High."
The first time I said that to him...
What?!
えっ？　橋高に？　ひなちゃんが？
Hashi High?!
Really?!
What?!
（ひなた）なぜだか 零ちゃんは
すっごく すっごく喜んでくれて…
What?!
For some reason, he was extremely happy.
Huh?
U-Um, I don't know if I'll get in yet.
あ… あの…　私
まだ受かるかどうかも分からないし
Um, I haven't even been going to a cram school.
えっと その…
塾とかにも行ってないし…
（ひなた）次の日には—
The next day, Rei came over with a study plan.
学習プランを携えて
我が家に来てくれ…
Fix
Serious
時間は
たっぷりあります
We have plenty of time.
今から準備すれば 絶対 大丈夫！
If we start preparing now, you'll definitely be all right!
（ひなた）
それからは 週に何回か—
Since then, he's been supervising my studies
several times a week after having dinner here.
うちで晩ご飯を食べたあと
勉強を見てくれることになりました
I-I think I'm starting to get the hang of it.
な… なんか少し コツっていうか…
Yeah, I think I've got it.
うん つかめてきたかも
Right?
でしょう？　数学は 何回も解いて
感覚をつかんでいくしかないんだよ
You can only get a feel for math
by solving problems over and over.
落ち着いて
１コ１コ解いていけば大丈夫
You'll be fine if you stay calm and solve them one at a time.
うん 頑張る！
Right. I'll do my best!
（ひなた）零君は
根気強く教えてくれるので—
Rei is a patient teacher,
Zzz
すごく分かりやすくて
ありがたいです
which makes this easy to understand, so I'm really grateful.
Zzz
ハッ！　こ… これは…
Ping
I-Is this a late-night snack I'm sensing?
お夜食の予感！
Peek
もしも〜し
Hello.
Do we have anyone here who would like to be pampered?
甘やかされたい人は
いますか？
Gasp
えっ？
それって もしかして…
Wait, could that be...
Yes!
はい！　はい
甘やかされたいです！
Rattle
Yes, I want to be pampered!
Pampered?
甘やかし？
よいしょっと…
Hup!
Steaming
パパ〜ン
Ta-da!
Steaming
（ひなた）わあ…
（あかり）はい
Here you are.
Simmer
Steaming
お揚げさんと天ぷらの
一緒のせですよ
Simmer
Steaming
Fried tofu and tempura together as toppings.
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
Steaming
Sweet
Simmer
こ… これが
川本家伝説の“甘やかしうどん”！
Th-This is the Kawamoto family's legendary "pampered noodles"!
プワップワに煮込まれた
とろける天ぷらに…
Melting tempura that's been deep-fried to fluffiness...
更に隣に ジュワッとお汁の染みた
甘〜いお揚げさん
next to sweet fried tofu permeated with sizzling broth!
おいしいものの隣に
また おいしいもの！
Something delicious
Something delicious right next to something delicious!
Mmm...
Glow
し… 幸せすぎる
I-It makes me too happy!
“甘やかしうどん”…
Pampered noodles...
う… うまっ！
D-Delicious!
So, which do you want with the noodles? Fried tofu, or tempura?
（美香子(みかこ)）さあ
きつねにする？　天ぷらにする？
I can't choose!
（あかり）そんなの選べないよ…
…という娘の悩みを
癒やすために開発された—
And so, to erase her daughter's troubles,
she came up with the cockamamie idea of using both.
この両方のせという暴挙！
She called it...
その名も…
Hee
Hee hee
Hee hee hee
“甘やかしうどん”！
pampered noodles!
（あかり）お母さんが 受験のとき
よく夜食に作ってくれたんだ
Mom often made it for me as a late-night snack when I was studying for entrance exams.
Eating that always made me really happy.
これ食べると
すっごく うれしかった
And I wanted to make it for you when it was your turn to study for exams, Hina.
だから 私も ひなのときには
絶対 作ったげようって思ってたの
Thanks.
うん うれしい
This makes me happy.
It's so delicious!
すっごく おいしい
（あかり）
さあ…　じゃ もうひと頑張りかな
Well,
I guess you have a little longer to go.
I left the heat on for the bath,
so turn it off when you're done.
お風呂 火ぃ落としてないから
最後 よろしくね
Okay.
（ひなた）
うん ありがとう　おやすみなさい
Thanks.
Goodnight!
零ちゃんの通っている私立高校に
行きたいと思ったとき—
When I first thought I wanted to go to the same private high school as Rei,
ただ“行ってみたい”って
気持ちだけで—
it was only the feeling of "I want to go."
I didn't know if it was okay to be selfish.
そんなわがまま言っていいのか
分からなかった
夏に屋台を出して
改めて気づいたのだ
When we set up a stand in the summer, it made me think.
（ひなた）この１コ250円の—
Within these small sweets that cost 250 yen apiece,
小さくて甘いお菓子の中に—
一体 どれだけの手間と時間と
お金が かかっているのだろう？
how much time, labor, and money has gone into them?
Starting at dawn, Grandpa stands in front of the stove on days he cooks bean jam.
あんこを炊く日は 夜明け前から
釜の前に立つおじいちゃん
そのおじいちゃんの
手に残るのは—
How much money is left for Grandpa from one of those sweets?
一体 １コ当たり どれだけ…
そして
私が私立に行くことになったら—
And if I went to a private high school,
how many sweets would Grandpa have to make?
そのためには おじいちゃんは—
一体 何コ お菓子を
こさえないといけないのだろう？
（相米二(そめじ)）行きなさい 駒橋高校
Go to Komahashi High School.
えっ？　で… でも…
Huh?
B-But...
（相米二）この夏 お前たちは
屋台 頑張ったな
You girls worked really hard with the stand this summer.
From calculating the cost to production to sales to the end, you did a great job.
原価の計算から 作って売って
締めの所まで よくやった
だから
気ぃ遣いのお前(めえ)のことだ—
But you're worried about something.
You're thinking how much income is left for me after making these sweets, right?
“じいちゃんが この菓子作って
どれだけアガリが残るのか”とか
考えちまったんだろう？
子供は
そんなこと考えなくてもいい
"Kids don't need to think about that stuff."
That's not how I feel.
…とは 俺は思わん
Money is precious.
金は大事だ
これは本当に大切なことだ
That's very important.
それに気づいたお前は立派だ
And I'm impressed you realized that.
だがな ひな
But, Hina...
Clang
you'd better not underestimate this old fart!
このじいちゃんを
ナメてもらっちゃ困る
Grin
...........
じいちゃんの菓子には
待ってくれてる人がいる
There are people waiting for my sweets.
だから 俺は まだまだ
あんこと格闘する気で満々だ
And I still have plenty of will left to tussle with that bean jam!
You want to go because that school would be fun.
“楽しそうだと思ったから”
いいじゃねえか！
That one reason is okay by me!
理由なんて それ１コでＯＫだ
じいちゃんはな
Whether or not you're enjoying your life is what matters the most to me.
お前が楽しく
過ごしてくれるのが
いちばんなんだ
Grandpa...
おじいちゃん…
（相米二）
う〜ん…　しかし 何つうか アレだ
But, hey, there's another thing.
Your sister and I looked into a few things.
姉ちゃんと
いろいろ調べてはみたんだが
Apparently the school that kid goes to,
Komahashi High School, is really tough to get into.
坊主の行ってる駒橋高校
偏差値 随分 高いらしいぞ
Augh
Are you gonna be able to get in?
お前 大丈夫なのか？
Shake
キャ〜ッ…　で… ですよね
G-Good question.
Shake
頑張る　頑張ろう
I'll do my best.
I'll work hard.
頑張って勉強して
あの高校に通うんだ
I'll study hard and get into that school!
え〜っと 零ちゃん
あのね ここなんだけど…
Um, Rei, I've got a question about this one.
零ちゃん…
Rei.
Shogi Checkmate Problems
（ひなた）
詰め将棋を解く零ちゃんは
吸い込まれるように静かで—
When Rei is solving shogi checkmate problems,
he gets quiet and absorbed.
私も つられて ものすごく集中した
The mood was infectious,
enabling me to have incredible concentration.
不思議なくらい シンとして
カーテンを開くと—
It was unusually silent,
so I opened the curtain.
窓の外は…
Outside the window...
今年初めての雪だった
was this year's first snow.
New Year
Surrounded by a landscape on the verge of permanent stasis
I found myself searching for something
I took up a mask to make my pitifully weak self appear stable
And donned it boldly
The sound of my frozen footsteps as I walked along the river
Was easily overpowered by the roar of a passing train
Yet I kept chanting "I just gotta take another step" to myself
Over and over again
Can you hear me proclaiming that I'm standing right here?
Even in bare feet I can go wherever the hell I want
I don't know where I might find myself at the end
I can't begin to guess, but I can just ink in
A new landscape to suit me as I go
Next Episode Preview
Episode 43
（ひなた）
試験まで あと５日…
Five more days until
the entrance exam.
Call for me if you need anything.
（零）
何かしてほしいことが
あったら 呼んで
I'll be right next door.
僕は隣にいるから
（ひなた）四国…
そんな遠い所に…
Shikoku?
That's so far away.
What the hell am I doing?
（零）
俺 何やってんだ…
（あかり）
お母さん おばあちゃん
Mom, Grandma,
please watch over Hina.
ひなを
どうか見守っていて
Illustration: Iwamoto Nao
The best late-night snack for entrance exams is...
（林田）
受験生の夜食といえば？
（野口）うどんですな
Wheat-flour noodles, right?
They digest quickly and are easy on the stomach.
消化がよく
おなかに優しいですぞ